[Music]
so a couple of days ago Jordan Peterson
put on his first film in quite a while
talking about his recent struggles with
benzodiazepines I think this is a really
really important story
Jordan Peterson being the most
high-profile case but it's affected
millions and millions of people and it's
actually something I've looked into
quite a lot I was looking into it for a
documentary a few years ago the
long-term effects of anti psychiatric
medication including benzodiazepines and
it's also a major case study for many of
the issues we've been talking about on
rebel wisdom the failures of journalism
and especially something that Eric
Weinstein has talked about the
distributed idea suppression complex or
disk which is why certain things are
talked about in the media and certain
things are not talked about how we get
consensus around misinformation and how
it ties in especially to what some
people are calling the meta crisis how
an outdated paradigm especially in
science and medicine is leading to
real-world outcomes and real-world harms
for a lot of people and it also raises
interesting questions about Jordan
Peterson's philosophy whether there were
blind spots that I hope he continues to
explore as he recovers to unpack the
story I talked to Robert Whittaker who's
an award-winning journalist who's
written many books about this subjects
including anatomy of an epidemic so I'm
gonna play quite a lot of clips from him
and then other clips of people we've
spoken to on the channel and try and
unpack this as a story so first things
first
Jordan Peterson's daughter Mikayla
didn't interview with him that she put
out on her channel a couple of days ago
where he talked about his history
--scent history with benzodiazepines and
also laid out a pretty stark warning to
people this is part of the reason we're
doing this this podcaster video is well
to let people know these are very widely
prescribed drugs and they are not safe
to take for more than two weeks or a
month at the absolute maximum and if you
take them longer than that and you end
up addicted
you're gonna or dependent which means
that you'll suffer withdrawal symptoms
on their cessation you are gonna be one
sorry person some people you know have a
better time of it when they stop their
use than others but enough people have a
terrible times so that it's an absolute
it's a it's a medically-induced epidemic
it's a complete bloody catastrophe here
it's probably worse than the opiate
epidemic and that's really saying
something so and I don't know if I'm out
of it or not you know I mean I'm I have
a hard time believing how much better I
feel than I did two weeks ago it's it's
it doesn't seem plausible he said he was
put on benzodiazepines for anxiety which
was sparked by a severe allergic
reaction to food but then developed a
dependency so as I said I looked into
this a while ago for a potential
documentary I read a lot of the books in
the area including cracked by James
Davies anatomy of an epidemic and mad in
America by Robert Whittaker and I knew
that Robert Whittaker who looked into
this for a very long time so I knew he
was the right person to contact so he's
a former investigative journalist with
the Boston Globe and the Boston Globe
has got a history of being one of the
best investigative papers in the u.s.
famously they broke the story of
pedophilia in the Catholic Church which
was the subject of the film spotlight
and Whitaker himself was shortlisted for
a pilot surprise who's a serious
researcher who knows this subject inside
out we're talking now specifically
because of the news about Jordan
Peterson and he just put out a video
yesterday talking about his history with
benzodiazepines and warning people not
to take them for more than two weeks
that this is that he's very worried
about those drugs
can you talk specifically about
benzodiazepines in this context what how
do they work and how does the brain kind
of compensate why are there so many dead
dead why is it so dangerous to be taking
them for a length of time yeah the
Wenzel story is really amazing because
doctors have known these drugs for a
long time cheating me taken laughing for
two or three weeks so that's not even
new knowledge that became like the
official recommendation in 1980 think of
a car as an accelerator it also has a
brake right and and that's how you sort
of maintain brain function because you
have molecules that can excite things of
any molecules that can quiet things
well the molecule that quiets things the
main molecules called gab
and so what happens is it with a with a
gaba neurotransmitter it inhibits the
firing of the second neuron it makes it
less likely to fire so it's a quiet
evening so what a benzodiazepine does is
it amps up the gaba system it's like
slamming the brake on on neuronal
activity so that's why you know that's
why you know your emotions you know you
feel relaxed so you don't care your
anxiety goes that's because the benzo
when you first take it it's quieting
your your your your your brain in
essence and your whole system and this
is why also if you know take too many
pencils just stop breathing right so
what what is again so what happens so
this is your braking system right so
you're going to benzo and benzo is
amplifying gaba it gets into the gaba
receptor so it acts as a gather
substitute so you bring those ah I'm not
doing too much inhibit inhibition
there's too much inhibitory of my
regular functioning so it starts
reducing its gaba receptors and its own
production of gaba so think about this
it's the normal break right now what you
do is with a drug you press harder on
that break alright like you put your
foot down but the brain brains own
breaking mechanism then starts becoming
less effective okay so now go off your
benzo right
what do you guys you've lost your
braking system or it's become diminished
so that's why for example you hear
people come off oh I've got these weird
skin sensations and all these things is
because your neurons are firing like
crazy out of control because you have
you have at the very least lessened that
natural braking system yeah I remember
reading your your work and it just seems
so clear that
the brain is a an adaptive system it's
adapting to the perturbations that
you're having from the from not just
benzos but all all psychiatric drugs and
then especially if you're taking it for
anxiety and your brain is then
effectively kind of ramping up the the
receptors for anxiety when you're coming
off then you are then super super
sensitized for the very thing that you
were trying to dull down in the first
place one thing I'd like to ask you
about because I've seen Jordan Peterson
and his daughter talk about that he was
prescribed it for a food allergy and
then increasingly over over time
developed what he described as a very
unusual reaction to two benzos where
they were actually making it more
anxious rather than less and from what I
understand from your work at least
that's not actually that unusual to that
you once over time you start to actually
become become more and more sensitized
to the very thing you're trying to block
what would you how are you reflect on
that no I think you just got a right no
I I mean this is part of the tragedy of
this whole thing that you come there for
some short relief and short-term relief
but you're setting yourself up if you
stay on these very long for it for a
difficult process either the difficult
thing of coming off or just as you said
because the brain has changed more
everyday anxiety and there there is a a
mechanism that explains it and the
mechanism that you're is if you're
taking away the brains on breaking
system so I'm releasing the whole
interview with Robert at the same time
as I'm releasing this film so Robert
lays out in detail how benzos are
particularly bad but all psychiatric
drugs have serious questions about their
long-term use in anatomy of an epidemic
when I did is I just look as a marker of
disability okay so I looked at the
number of people who were ending up on
government disability due to mental
illness okay now that's the extreme
right they can no longer work well in
1987 we had about
1.25 million adults on disability due to
mental illness okay then we get this s1
prozac comes to market we get this
explosion in the use of drugs and now
today it's around five million adults on
disability United States and by the way
it's caught up in every country I can
find that embrace this story and the use
of antidepressants and all like in the
UK nor you know in Scandinavian
countries Australia New Zealand you see
it over and over again the second thing
is like what's happening to the kids so
you see with this increasing use of
psychiatric drugs the mental health of
kids is deteriorating in the United
States something like well first of all
just on disability in 1987 when prozac
came to market we had 16,000 kids whose
families or guardians received a payment
because the kid was too sick the child
is disabled by mental illness it's
something like seven or eight hundred
thousand so you know that's like what is
that a forty time in Crete 40-fold
increase and if you look at kids who end
up psychiatrist and sort of you know if
they end up on disability two thirds
going to adult disability but they turn
age eighteen but the most amazing thing
is something like fifty percent of
American students now seek mental health
during their four years of college so I
see this disability like a canary in the
coal mine go coal mine in other words
that's that's a marker of harm done but
all the markers suicides gone up like 20
years in a row in the United States the
burden of depression globally has
increased dramatically and I'm not
saying it's only due to the drugs but
all the markers of psychiatric distress
and developed societies have basically
gone up in the last thirty years
so that's on just on if we just see this
as
a story of a medical failure okay if we
just look at this through of medical
lens the larger failure is this is also
a story of philosophy because think
about what the chemical imbalance story
is telling you it's telling you that
these chemicals your brain control you
right that you're sort of the the robot
through these master chemicals and it
takes away a sense of of responsibility
for oneself right because it's not your
responsibility that you're unhappy or
whatever whereas if you have a different
philosophy and the philosophy is listen
to suffer is to be human we're gonna be
anxious
we're gonna meet impressed sometimes and
even to go a bit mad is not all that
unusual especially if you stop sleeping
and stuff but if we have like an older
style of that first of all we have a you
know if we look at it as a philosophy
you see in novels and Shakespeare and
all we understand that humans suffer we
also understand that the human mind is
not a pleasant place sometimes it's a
difficult place that becomes your
philosophy of understanding what it
means to be human it ain't easy growing
up being easy so when you suffer you're
depressed you're breathing okay and
you're bit crazy that's what humans are
so let's be really clear what we're
talking about here
Jordan Peterson along with many many
others became seriously debilitating the
ill just from following the doctor's
advice what does it say about our
society what does it say about our
culture that this is happening to so
many people so partly as Daniel SHM
Acton Berger laid out in our war on
sense-making film we've got an incentive
structure that pushes the pharmaceutical
companies towards more and more
lucrative models wherever there is a any
misalignment in agency and there's the
ability to share signal for strategic
purposes then you have a basis to have
signal that's being shared that isn't
just truthful
right so then we look at well where is
that happening and it's fucking
everywhere right - really gross or
subtle degrees pretty much everywhere
and sometimes for dreadful purposes like
I mean you got the prosaic purposes
which are basically market type dynamics
which most of the dynamics in the world
or market dynamics or at least
influenced by market dynamics right
market dynamics are fundamentally at
least partially if not mostly reverse
meaning my balance sheet can get ahead
independent of your balance sheet
getting ahead and definitely independent
of the Commons as a company I want to do
sense making for you because I want to
control your choice making and to the
degree that my fiduciary responsibility
is to maximize profitability for me and
my shareholders and so I need to
maximize lifetime revenue of my
customers multiplied by maximizing the
customer base addiction is the most
profitable thing I can get right where
that's never in the best interest of the
customer but we've also got a problem
where we cannot really trust a lot of
science the essence of science within
the philosophy of science the essence of
it is earnestness of inquiry right it's
empiricism but then earnestness of
inquiry eddington define science as the
earnest endeavor to put into order the
facts of experience and the essence of
capitalism is so you can say the essence
of science is no bias right at least the
idea the spirit of it we can get into
where even the philosophy of science has
built in axiomatic bias later but then
the in capitalism it is about optimizing
for bias right like I actually have in
an agency that I'm trying to get ahead I
have intention to increase my balance
sheet and so if there's capital funding
of science it's going to fund the things
that create ROI on that research so we
can keep doing more research that
creates both a reason to distort the
info and the reason to withhold
information that is a source of
competitive advantage a reason to create
disinfo like to just move the
conversation on to the question of the
media and the
incentive structures and why is this
story not being told I remember reading
your book and looking at other books and
this topic as well and just feeling
incredibly angry at the level of by the
level of harm that is caused by this and
just that the level of silence that
seems to be on the part of of the media
and on the part of kind of the
institutions how is that maintained how
is that kind of this story maintained
it's a really good question
and it seems hard to imagine that it
could have been maintained as well as it
has there's a couple things the media
doesn't really know the science right
because you really have to dig into this
you have to understand house a site
about drug testing how you can bias
trials by design you know there's a lot
of different ways you also have to read
the whole studies you don't just read
the abstract so the first problem is
even science reporters generally don't
know this literature not really okay
what they know is what the people they
interview tell now which are academic
psychiatrists and all so why don't we
know this story one is because American
psychiatry basically closed ranks in the
night early 1980s and said this is the
story we're going to tell and they even
had training workshops where they taught
that psychiatrist to tell this story and
the idea was psychiatry in the 70s was
sort of a discipline and disrepute or
fearing for its survival and if they put
on the white coat both literally and
metaphorically here figurative they
could now present themselves to it sort
of the image of infectious disease
doctors remember how celebrated
infectious disease doctors heart because
we we know minimize of infectious
disease with the arrival of the
antibiotics
anyway they decided and you can you can
really see this psychiatry decided to
tell a story in nineteen eighty these
are brain illnesses therefore were real
doctors are drugs are good and really we
if these are illnesses it doesn't really
help to say that talk therapy split
right there medical illnesses and what
do you do with medical illnesses you you
have a drug and who can prescribe drugs
at psychiatrist so that's the first
thing the second thing is who really
love this story
pharmaceutical companies because now
you're gonna take all these ills that
human beings then you can't get it you
can't pass a drug front happiness okay
you can pass a drug for a medical
condition called anxiety or depression
so they were gonna take all these ills
that human being suffer all the time
there's you know beyond the asylum and
now they're gonna make them diseases and
that's gonna open up the market so what
happened you see that the front suitable
companies start paying academic
psychiatrist to be their advisors
consultants you know that sort of thing
speakers advisors consultants now and
I'm talking about a lot of money so what
are the pharmaceutical thing companies
think they were doing when they were
hiring these academic psychiatrist they
thought they were building markets in
other ways what did the academic
psychiatrist I'm thinking I'm so
brilliant I'm a world expert that I
deserve five hundred thousand dollars
for going on a speaking tour doing this
research or consulting and you know the
old thing it's hard to convince a man of
anything here or a person of anything if
it goes against their financial
well-being that the actual sentiment is
much more concise than that once the
profession said to themselves this is
the story we're going to tell they're
gonna start believing that story and
then and and and they're gonna start
seeing whatever bits of science that can
support that story that's what they're
gonna go on to and they're gonna find a
way to either ignore or discount or even
keep out of their journals some of the
stuff that challenge that and what you
see quite clearly
American psychiatric history those
psychiatrists who broke with that and
wanted to publish other types of
research they got killed by killed I
mean their careers went down the tubes
so that became a clear message that we
are going from psychiatry supported by
pharmaceutical money and as Whitaker
lays out in anatomy of an epidemic many
people find themselves in this catch-22
kind of almost calf caressed position
where they go to the doctor and get a
certain diagnosis of maybe anxiety or
depression and a prescription they then
find the drug has serious effects side
effects well they're not really side
effects that the effects of the drug but
then any of those effects of the drug
they then maybe get moved on to a
different drug or a cocktail of drugs
and any of the effects of the drug are
then often attributed to their initial
diagnosis their initial condition so
very rarely other side effects or the
effects linked to the drugs themselves
can you talk about that sort of catch-22
situation that people find themselves in
and how that plays out just an up sort
of a bigger picture well in a way I
think you've summarized a quick look
that's great well that's exactly right
so what happens is so you you start down
this path okay and often you get down
this path with just a mild problem right
you come in you have a mild problem
you're looking for maybe you got divorce
oh you lost a job or something has
happened okay
maybe you're not sleeping and so you
start down this path where your brain is
gonna be changed by the drug and as we
were discussing earlier very often it
poops out the positive effect it's sort
of control of the symptoms poops out
over time right so what happens when it
poops out
do you blame and and maybe new symptoms
are coming up right oh I wasn't
depressed before nothing at rest I
wasn't anxious before now I'm anxious
the proper medical thing would be to say
ah the drug has stopped working and
maybe it's indeed inducing this problems
that's the iatrogenic ban but people who
prescribe drugs don't want to admit that
their drugs are doing harm they only
want to see them through a prism of
doing help even though we all know that
drugs can do harm that's not how the
prescriber
or the you know the medical profession
of psychiatry wants to see its drugs so
what they do is as they start saying
that people are treatment resistant or
you know it's the illness that is what
you're seeing now is the illness
returned and once that happens what
happens you go on a second drug you go
on a third drug go on a fourth drug now
if you started wanting unipod for drugs
that's a sign of medical failure right I
mean no one says polypharmacy is good
and what it means is you've you started
having new symptoms and so you're moving
to new symptoms new dysfunction and once
you get on four or five drugs but I mean
it's hard to function well on four or
five drugs and you can't imagine the
number of the stories oh you can't
there's so many stories like I went on
just the other night I met it I was in
it I was talking to someone who did in
their sophomore year of college they
broke up with her girlfriends and as a
result failed chemistry so he was put on
the benzo was anxious 32 years later he
was trying to tape her from the benzo
he wasn't working he did on any number
of drugs it all started when he broke up
with his girlfriend like he's 20 years
old but that's part of the narrative
that really is a misleads the public
with that when people when you see
people deteriorate on these medications
long term it's blamed to the disease
even though there's no evidence that
this is the natural course of things and
in that way they they preserve they
preserve the image of the drugs as as
you know as helpful and all the problems
get assigned to the disease but there's
no evidence for that and and and David
one thing I think that's really
important here what's the natural course
of these problems because in order to
assess whether a drug is doing harm
over the long term okay or providing a
benefit you have to know the natural
course what is the natural capacity to
recover and so what is the long-term
course your drug in order to be
beneficial has to beat that natural
recovery rate so let's say the natural
recovery rate from depression is 80%
which otherwise what it used to be
called and and and that two years later
let's say 80% are not depressed okay for
your drug to be beneficial over two
years you have to have overcoming
reading like 85% and what you don't see
that will seem like actually recovering
rate on the presence is terrible but in
the best long in a in a couple long-term
studies we had the United States you
know stay well rate was at the end of
one year in real clinical settings and
when it was three percent and and the
other was about it was about six percent
and as the the researcher said these are
astonishingly low you know stay well
rates and when they did those studies
they said these are real-world studies
we're not gonna be doing these pharma
funded studies where you're you're
trying to pick a select group of people
now at the same time it's but anyway so
what are you doing you're taking a
national recovery rate and you're
lowering this was always one of my
puzzles with Jordan Peterson's
philosophy and worldview is because he
was so critical of the New Atheists
they're sort of reductionistic a
materialistic view of the world and how
it left no space for the soul this is
why I have such frustration say with
people like Sam Harris this sort of
radical atheists because they seem to
think that once human beings abandoned
their their grounding in the
transcendent that the the plausible way
forward is with a kind of purist
rationality that automatically
attributes to other people equivalent
value it's like I just don't understand
that but I never saw him draw that kind
of obvious next step which is what kind
of world does that worldview or that
philosophy create the reduction of the
world to only what you can measure and
quantify and the reduction of the human
being to only the
McCall's and the processors and this
area of psychiatric drug psychiatric
intervention is one of the most obvious
examples of where that philosophy is
lacking I don't think we understand the
psyche at all as Robert explains it
starts from a sort of mechanistic view
of human beings right and and and of
course medicine did advance in many ways
from a mechanistic point of view you
don't understood the heart and at the
same time I think medicine as a whole is
faltered for that because I'm not seeing
that these holistic you know these we're
not just a heart we're not just this
system we're not just that system that
all these things are interrelated I mean
we're talking physically now right and
letting getting in some cuts into the
brain but now add in the brain and now I
didn't consciousness now and it's an
unbelievable ability to feel and know
the world and know a little bit about
your mind at least a conscious part I
think if you go through human history
right that we can and people societies
are trying to understand themselves and
they tell stories of that like how we
got here what is our relationship to
nature and what is the my and God know
there's a mystery to it there's a
profundity to it so we often saw Jordan
Peterson defending the current system
and in some ways defending the status
quo for obvious and justified reasons
the Western tradition of free speech the
necessity of hierarchies of competence
the sheer unlikely 'no sub having a
functioning civilization at all and
gratitude for that but we didn't often
see him point out the corrupting
influences on the system or the
drawbacks of the current system and in
some ways the increasing
dysfunctionality of that system so the
first film that really put rebel wisdom
on the map was glitching the matrix
Jordan Peterson the mainstream media and
the intellectual dark web the follow-up
to that was called glitch in the matrix
- and was called the origin story of
the intellectual darkweb with Eric
Weinstein the man who came up with the
turn and in that he looked really
carefully at the structure of
institutions how groupthink arrives how
consensus is built around false
narratives and the damage that that's
done to society
so in general when I hear the word
consensus my initial hit on the word
consensus is negative why is that it's
because if everybody agrees that
something is true like two plus three
equals five you don't need a consensus
nobody talks about the arithmetic
consensus everybody who doesn't
subscribe to the arithmetic consensus
goes nowhere they can't build a house
they can't you know I handle money okay
so there is no need to call it the
arithmetic consensus on the other hand
if things are actually open-ended very
rare for people to all bunched together
around one set of tentative ideas so
what you find is that in general you
would expect a cacophony of people each
with their own pet ideas when things are
genuinely uncertain or you would find
everybody falling in line when more or
less it's clear that that the world goes
one particular way so in general I think
what's going on with the consensus is
that a consensus is usually achieved
through some sort of incentivizing
people as the as the mobs the violent
mobs in Mexico say Plateau Oh Plomo do
you want silver or do you want lead so
you're given a certain amount of
encouragement to come to a particular
perspective maybe in terms of grant
money or speaking opportunities and
you're given a disincentive which is
this is what's going to happen to your
career if you don't fall in line and he
also coined the term the distributed
information suppression complex or the
disc to talk about how inconvenient
narratives were kept out of the
conversation do you want to talk a
little bit about what the disc is and
why you think it's so important sure if
you went back to the first Matrix movie
let's say clearly it's a sci-fi thriller
to ask yourself was it fiction at all is
the reason that that movie did so well
and played so well that in fact it
wasn't fiction but metaphor and I think
that there's some point at which
Morpheus starts describing the matrix in
the film as a prison that you cannot see
taste feel or touch or something like
that in some sense the disc works like
this we've lived our entire lives in a
medium and that medium has to do with
the way in which our ideas are
suppressed long story short is that
there were a lot of storytelling
influences that made it difficult for
critics and there was a lot of money and
power and prestige behind the
conventional narrative yeah it's I find
it really interesting we there's another
person we've had on the channel quite a
bit called Erik Weinstein when we talks
about the he's called so he's come up
with a term the disc the distributed
information suppression complex and I
think you know yeah I think it fits
perfectly with this he basically
describes how in many different areas of
many different institutions they
coalesce around certain narratives for
prestige and financial and other kind of
incentive structures and then anyone who
deviates from that is like taken out
because if the platter or Plomo so
you're either bought off or you're
dispatched that it comes from me I think
what's his name Escobar you're gonna
kind of keep people in line in Medellin
in Colombia by either bribery or or
assassination and he he talks about this
in I think this is the one of the the
most obvious examples of how that system
works that I've that I've seen yeah that
said exactly what happened that's a
brilliant way of summarizing yeah and
you know what brilliant about this as
you can see the incentives I mean and
you can see who benefits from this
so you can see why you would have this
sort of thing in operation
that's a brilliant that I love that sort
of acronym - that's a great what what
drives you in this in this work what why
are you sort of blowing this furrow and
have you felt a bit of a lonely battle
over the years there are elements of
loneliness that's for sure there are
also elements of great reward and the
reward comes from this counter narrative
let's call it a counter Nair and I've
been talking about well it's it's
getting more and more accepted it's
growing okay
and it's making inroads even into you
know journals and that sort of things I
can't read journals so there is some
reward for pursuing a counter narrative
that even as time goes by gets stronger
not weaker like new evidence just
continues to come along that supports
your counter narrative no and and
revealing the falseness of the you know
of the conventional so there's something
rewarding about that I've had so many
many many many people write me and say
ah now I understand my life I got I got
screwed up on these drugs and many now
so often it's hard to get off these
drugs okay but I know many people have
and they feel like they got their lives
back and of course it's rewarding to be
part of them an underdog fought battle
right David versus Goliath that's always
fun
that said it's tough because you get
excommunicated people think you're a
little nutty or something happens how
could you be the how could you be the
one that understands things better you
know how can your narrative be better
than been there to put together by the
American Psychiatric Association and I
say well it's not - it's actually good
their science not my science what's
wearying though okay so I need by the
way did you meet so many great people
engaged human people humanistic people
you also have the joy of you know in
journalism Neil the adage of like
afflict the comfortable and comfort the
afflicted and here you feel so often
your comforting the afflicted and
afflicting the comforter and that's
pretty great and as Robert said one of
the reasons this is not talked about so
much in the media is that we're dealing
with vulnerable people in difficult
situations and no editor wants to put
the message out there that says everyone
should stop taking their drugs and it's
important to say that the drugs have
very good effect in the short term in
acute conditions and I also feel a
certain sense of responsibility to point
to some things that do seem to work one
of the most promising interventions when
I was looking into this a couple of
years ago was something called open
dialogue which is an intervention where
a number of therapists and the family of
the person who's suffering come together
and talk about what's going on and set
up some kind of support systems for the
person in trouble this was doing really
well in some of the Nordic countries and
in Germany and they were even looking at
it for a trial in the UK and the NHS I
think the thing that struck many of us
during Jordan Peterson's kind of
meteoric rise to fame was this sense of
intimacy and connection with his
audience in some ways he was like a
perfect YouTube star in that way you got
a real sense he was very open about what
was going on you got to see his inside
his life in many ways and also he had a
real level of self awareness like he was
constantly inquiring and asking
questions about what was happening to
him and was aware enough of how the
process was affecting him in negative
ways as well it's not like the media
exposure although it's been stressful
it's not like I'm not grateful for it
even people who've put me on the spot
very badly have ended up doing me a
tremendous favor but the problem is is
that because
the problem is I'm becoming too much on
garden and I've noticed a developing
sense of impatience within me and some
suspicion and that's not good
I don't want to be in situations where
those are my fundamental orientations
it's it's a it's a sign of a certain
amount of internal corruption on my part
so hopefully Jordan Peterson has turned
a corner in his recovery and will
continue to get better and I'd love to
have a conversation with him sometime
soon and ask him given that he has ended
up in this position just by following
doctor's orders just by doing what he
was advised to do whether it's given him
any new thoughts or insights into the
wider problems with the system the wider
corruptions with the system and the
systemic meta crisis that's caused by
this very reductionistic worldview so
take care see you soon rebel wisdom was
set up to make sense of the world at a
deeper level than the mainstream media
it was built for these times of crisis
and change which is why we want to do
what we can to meet the challenge of the
times more films and also for our rebel
wisdom members weekly sense-making calls
with our amazing interviewees and also
we're introducing the wisdom gym a place
to practice some of the skills that
we've talked about on the channel thanks
for watching and see you soon
[Music]